A Guide to the Ford Foundation records, Office of Communications, Vice President, Office Files of Marta Tellado FA1378
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation records, Office of Communications, Vice President, Office Files of Marta Tellado
1949-2009
Rockefeller Archive Center
Ford Foundation
Tellado, Marta
FA1378
0.76 Cubic Feet 2 document boxes: 2 letter size boxes
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Ford Foundation archive was deposited at the RAC in 2011. Ford Foundation records, correspondence, reports, program files, and officers' papers were transferred to and accessioned by the RAC beginning in 2011. Accessions continue as necessary.
This material was transferred to the RAC in two accessions between 2023 and 2024 and was ingested by the RAC as Accessions 2023:078 and 2024:012.
Conditions Governing Access
Open for research. Brittle or damaged items are available at the discretion of RAC.
Scope and Contents
The collection contains the office files Marta Tellado created when she served as Vice President of the Ford Foundation's Office of Communications. It consists of one series of subject files documenting Tellado's activities as Communications Vice President.
Tellado's files show the Office of Communication's duties for promotion and commentary on the Ford Foundation's programming and operations. The programs the Foundation funded, its decisions for funding, and how it funded its grantees are largely the focus of the communication subjects documented within the collection.
In addition to records related to communication strategy and preparation, material formats found throughout the collection include correspondence, memos, reports, drafts, notes, meeting materials, and a couple images.
Arrangement
Collection is comprised of one series.
Original order was maintained as much as possible.
The collection arrangement is as follows:
Series 1. Subject files, 1949-2009
Ford Foundation; Public relations; Education, Higher
- Subject files, 1949-2009; 1; .76 Cubic Feet 2 document boxes: 2 letter size boxes
  Scope and Contents
  This series contains the subject files Marta Tellado created and maintained when she served as Vice President of the Ford Foundation's Office of Communications. Tellado's files document the Office of Communications' activities related to publicity and outreach regarding the Foundation's operations, programming, and background.
  Files in the series contain materials like communication plans, facts lists, summaries, draft questions and answers, talking points, and frequently asked question lists which show how the Communications Office prepared and carried out promotion and response. Other materials pertain to event planning and include invitations lists and invites. There are also reports and other historical information records the Communications Office gathered upon request and to inform contemporary public relations matters.
  Many of the files in the series document the Communication Office's response and commentary on the Michigan Attorney General's information request on the Foundation and controversial changes to the Foundation's grant letter language.
  Some of the materials in the series were created by Tellado's Communications Vice President predecessor, Alex Wilde. Tellado likely inherited these files. There are also records showing Tellado searching for these documents for requests.
  - Ann Dunham Sutero, information regarding, 2007 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    The file includes a computer print of a photograph of Ford Foundation staff. The photograph was submitted to the Office of Communications by Dessie Tasik in response to information gathering efforts about Ann Dunham Sutero's work history in the Ford Foundation's Jakarta, Indonesia Office. There is a photo index that describes people depicted within it. The individuals include: Mike Morfit, Terry Bigalke, Tom Kissinger, Dessie Tasik, Ann Sutero, William Carmichael, and Franklin Thomas.
  - International Fellowship Program (IFP) launch, 2000-2005 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Partnership for Higher Education in Africa, 2004-2005 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Partnership for Higher Education in Africa - Invitation list, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Partnership for Higher Education in Africa - Event planning, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Partnership for Higher Education in Africa, 2005 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Ford Foundation and Michigan preparation book, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Ford Foundation and Michigan preparation book II, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Michigan House Bill on Foundations 6153, June 7, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Michigan House Bill on Foundations 6535, September 19, 2006 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Stanley Surrey report on the tax aspects of the Ford Foundation's operations and correspondence, 1949-2006 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - 1950 Report of the Trustees of the Ford Foundation, 1950-1954 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Association of Community Organizations for Reform Now (ACORN) - Linda Simmons documents request, 2003-2009 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - September 11 New York City terrorist attacks philanthropic response - Tom Sessel reports, 2002-2003 (Box 1, Folder 14-15)
  - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU) – Ford Foundation grant letter language, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Ford Foundation building landmark presentation, 1967-1998 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    The file includes an image of the Ford Foundation's building exterior.
  - Ford Foundation Michigan grant actions, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Michigan Attorney General information request – Notes, facts, talking points, 2005-2006 (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Myths and facts - Ford Foundation operations and Michigan relationship, 2006 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Stanley Surrey Tentative Memorandum on the Tax Aspects of the Ford Foundation, 1949 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Edwin Black, Feature Group News Service - Correspondence, 2003 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Reports - Ford Foundation grantmaking in Palestinian territories and follow up to United Nation Forum of Non-Governmental Organizations, Durban, South Africa, circa 2001-2004 (Box 2, Folder 23)
  - New grant letter language - Universities, 2004 (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - New grant letter language - American Civil Liberties Union (ACLU), 2004 (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - New grant letter language, 2003-2004 (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - American Association of University Professors (AAUP) conference on academic boycotts, 1958-2006 (Box 2, Folder 27-28)